Finding aid to Jill Ker Conway Personal Papers CA.MS.01030
Smith College Archives
Jill Ker Conway Personal Papers
1934-2018
Smith College Archives
Conway, Jill Ker
CA.MS.01030
5.25 linear feet (3 record cartons, 1 full document box, 1 flat oversize box, 1 large card file)
1 items (1 CD)
Jill Ker Conway was the first female president of the college. Her selection, a watershed in the history of Smith, was also a hallmark in an era of significant change in the perception of women and their role in society. This collection of personal materials includes correspondence, photographs, professional and conference materials, awards, and memorabilia documenting Conway's personal life (1934-2018) and post-Smith career (1975-2018).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Originally in Conway's houses in Boston and Conway, MA; materials are a bequest from JKC, through Executor of her estate, Susie Bourque.
Biographical / Historical
Jill Ker Conway was the first female president of the college. Her selection, a watershed in the history of Smith, was also a hallmark in an era of significant change in the perception of women and their role in society. In her inaugural address, she stressed the importance of not only supporting women through their undergraduate education, but furthering the college mission "...to foster research and the creation of new knowledge about matters of central importance in women's lives." Some of the most significant accomplishments of her tenure reflect this vision. She focused much of her energy on developing and funding women-centered projects such as the Smith Management Program, Ada Comstock Program, and Project on Women and Social Change. Conway was only 39 years old when she accepted the Smith appointment in 1974. A native of New South Wales, Australia, she received her undergraduate education at the University of Sydney (1958). Two years after completing her B.A., she left Australia to pursue her Ph.D. at Harvard University. While at Harvard, she met and married John Conway, a Canadian historian and a native of Toronto. Together they moved to Canada where both obtained positions at the University of Toronto. Jill Conway remained at the University of Toronto for more than ten years, beginning in 1964. She began as a professor of U.S. social and intellectual history, then gradually rose through the administrative ranks to serve as the vice-president for internal affairs (1973-1975). Conway assumed the Smith presidency in July 1975. Several administrative and curricular changes were enacted during her tenure. Administrative offices, such as the Career Development Office (previously the Vocational Office), Dean of the College, Dean of Students, and Public Relations, were reorganized. The Women's Studies, Comparative Literature, Peace and War Studies, and Engineering Dual Degree programs were added to the curriculum during this period, and academic minors were introduced. Lasting physical reminders of her presidency include the Ainsworth Gym, expanded outdoor athletic facilities, as well as renovation and additions to Neilson Library. The Alumnae Gymnasium was also renovated during this period, and became home to the Smith College Archives, the Sophia Smith Collection, and the Nonprint Resource Center. Following her departure from the college in 1985, Conway has been a visiting professor in MIT's Program in Science, Technology, and Society. She has also authored and edited a number of books of fiction and nonfiction. Three volumes of her memoirs provide detailed biographical information about Conway. The third volume (released October 2001), chronicles her years at Smith. While this volume deals with Conway's personal as well as professional development, and is admittedly from a singular perspective, it can serve as a guide to the major developments of Smith College during her tenure.
Other Finding Aids
There is an unprocessed and closed collection of Jill Ker Conway Personal Papers that only has a print finding aid (no online records).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Related Materials
Jill Ker Conway's professional papers and materials can also be found in RG 32.01.
Separated Materials
Jill Ker Conway's christening gown (circa 1934) has been separated from this collection and transferred to the Smith College Historic Clothing Collection.
CDs; Electronic records; Photographs.; Publications; Bourque, Susan C.; Conway, Jill Ker; Conway, John J.; Bourque, Susan C.
- Jill Ker Conway personal papers and memorabilia, 2018-A-0062; 5.75 linear feet (3 record cartons, 1 full document box, 2 flat oversize boxes, 1 large card file)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, photographs, professional and conference materials, awards, and memorabilia documenting Conway's personal life (1934-2018) and post-Smith career (1975-2018).
  - I. Biographical Information, 1993-2013; 1; 12 folders (12 folders)
    - Articles and profiles written about Jill Ker Conway, 1973-2015; 13 folders (13 folders) (Box 1, Box 4, Box 5)
    - Companion of the Order of Australia award (news clippings, correspondence, photographs, program), 2013; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Family correspondence and information on the Adames estate, 1997-1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - National Humanities medal (news clippings, correspondence, photographs), 2012-2013; 3 folders (3 folder) (Box 1)
    - Publications related to Jill Ker Conway, 1999, 2002, 2014; 3 items (3 books/booklets) (Box 2)
  - II. Correspondence, 1974-2010; 2; 3 folders (3 folders)
    - Personal correspondence, mostly incoming, 1974-2009; 1 folders (Box 4)
    - Condolences for the death of John J. Conway, 1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and notes related to John J. Conway's memoir, 2010; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 4)
  - III. Teaching and Professional Affiliations, 2003-2014; 3; 11 folders (11 folders)
    - Bennett College, 2004; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Boston Museum project, 2003; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Daily planner, 2010, 2011, 2015, 2016; 4 folders (4 books) (Box 1)
    - Darwin College Cambridge membership, 2003; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Harvard Nike case study, 2014; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - University of Toronto, "History of Women in the United States, 1790-1940" class syllabus, 1972-1973; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - IV. Writings and Speeches, 1970-2015; 4; 1.5 linear feet (1 record carton, plus 44 folders in a second record carton)
    - 2005 speeches: On the Cusp, Examiners W RH, BSR, Georgetown, UNB, Citizen Conf., 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 1)
      - "On the Cusp," Jill Ker Conway at MIT, 2005; 1 items (1 CD) (Box 1)
    - 2006 speeches: ML private client, Athenaium, Town of Conway, Helmund, U of Sydney, Conway House dedication (Smith), Boston College, 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2007 speeches: Common Ground, Cam/Ox, M. Mitchell, Taste of Reading, Hamilton Trust, NEC, Mt. St. Vincent, Davis Symposium, 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2008 speeches: BC, Decourtivron, MacLeish, Smith College, The Mount, Madison U, Ceres, Conway School, 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2009 speeches: Chilton Centennial, Springfield, 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2010 speeches: Examiner Club, Lincoln School, Smith College, Grand Valley, Monmouth, 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2011 speeches: St. Catherine's, Smith College, 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 2012 speeches: Miss Hall's, Smith Club, Smith Alum, Smith Scholars, Aurora Foundation, ACAD at Charlemont, 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - Academic articles, 1970-1990; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Writing contributions, 2004-2007; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - M. Graubard files, 2004-2005; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Essays on individuals, 2006-2007; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Essays on politics, 2008; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Publisher correspondence and contracts, 1988-2002; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - Jill Ker Conway dissertation notes, 1960-1962; .5 linear feet (1 large card file box) (Box 3)
    - Written by Herself: Autobiographies of American Women Vol. I-III, edited by Jill Ker Conway, 1992; 3 items (3 books) (Box 6)
    - Dædalus, 1963, 1969, Winter 1985, Fall 1987, Fall 2005; 6 items (3 books, 3 booklets in an envelope) (Box 6)
    - Business Archives and History Vol. I, No 9, and Vol. II, No 1, 1961 August, 1962 February; 2 items (2 books) (Box 6)
  - V. Photographs, 1934-2009; 5; 38 items (23 folders plus 15 large photos in the flat box)
    - Coorain, Australia photographs, 1995; 2 items (2 photographs) (Box 4)
    - Family and vacation photographs, 1934-2008; 13 folders (13 folders and envelopes) (Box 4)
    - Smith College, 1975-1980, 2002; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Jill Ker Conway professional activity photos, 1975-2007; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Jill Ker Conway portraits and photos, 1959-2009; 14 items (4 folders and 10 large prints) (Box 4, Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, "A Decade of Achievement: Jill Ker Conway", 1975-1985; 1 items (1 book) (Box 5)
    - Photo album, pictures of an orange cat, approximately 1995; 1 items (1 album) (Box 6)
    - Photo album, scattering John J. Conway's ashes, 1995 August; 1 items (1 album) (Box 6)
    - Photo album, Smith College Commencement, 1985; 1 items (1 album) (Box 6)
    - Photo album, "Visiting Jill", 2004 August; 1 items (1 item) (Box 6)
  - VI. Artifacts, 6
    - Passports, Australian and American, 1960, 1965,1970, 1975, 1982, 1986, 1996; 7 items (Box 6)
    - Montgomery Fellow award from the New Hampshire Association for Women in Education, 1998 April 8; 1 items (1 item) (Box 6)
    - Mortarboard, 1969; 1 items (1 item) (Box 6)
    - Golden Door Award, 1985 December 10; 1 items (1 item) (Box 6)
    - Smith College Pioneers Hall of Fame plaque, 2014; 1 items (1 item) (Box 6)